—I am not a man of faith. I, myself, consider myself
a man of deeds, a man of action.
What I think, I do. As we say in Mexico:
"Saying and doing." I prefer experience and not belief.
There is an abysmal difference between believing and living it: the action, the facts.
Don't tell me you love me, show it.
Prove it! That's the action. That is the fact; and without saying anything,
you can say a lot... By doing things.
—I met you from a video in which you talked about Impeccability.
Could you explain to me what Impeccability is?
—To be impeccable is to be of one piece. That means that as you think, you have to live.
As you think, you have to eat. As you think, it has to be your complete life.
It's being true!
Testing is always around the corner. One person claims to be the best walker,
and around the corner you start to limp.
Part of that concept led people to acquire a true face.
And why do I say this? Because, what, we don't have a face?
No! We have masks.
Masks for everything: At home, with friends,
with siblings, with your girlfriend, with work...
But we don't give real faces.
We hide, we keep... So, part of that Impeccability is that:
Acquiring a true face, which also means being a Toltec:
He who dialogues with his own heart.
I believe that any knowledge of the world is available to human beings
for their own transcendence. If not, what's the joke?
So much knowledge?
Just like that, as scholars or as bookworms?
You have to live it!
You have to live it.
You yourself, now that you travel so much, right?
You could read books and books and books and encyclopedias about the places...
How different it is to go to them! No?
And living and being with the people, the road, the jungle,
the cold, the heat, the food... The experience is something else!
And experience, well, it will guide your criteria.
Then it will no longer be a belief!
Now it's going to be experience.
And that is part of the ancient knowledge of Mexico,
Toltec: Impeccability.
Be a man of own experience.
Do not be guided by beliefs or things of faith.
You live it! Experience it. ...And then, we talked.
—Experience is my greatest asset, it is my best capital. That's why I'm here.
—Because that experience is going to go with you.
It will be energetically marked in your being.
It will accompany you wherever you go.
Whether it is or whether other forms of life do not exist,
they will accompany you.
That is part, I believe, of our elements...
Right? ...in this life to be able to be understanding,
To be able to understand.
Because understanding is very difficult, right?
The word sounds easy, "understand," but coming to understand changes your life.
A Mexican poet named Nezahualcóyotl said,
"At last my heart understands:
I hear a song, And I see a flower:
May they not wither! May they not wither!"
He understood that he was going to die.
—"Do we come to live in vain?
To sprout on the Earth? —Mmm, there it is!
Let's at least leave flowers, Let's at least leave songs."
-That's how it is! —It's his, isn't it?
-Is he! "Let us at least leave flowers and at least songs,"
because perhaps, there, on the other side, in the region of mystery,
the flowers will end and the songs will end.
But here, on Earth...
Nobody!
Nobody can put an end to the flowers and the songs.
—I finally understood!
I didn't know that was why.
-You see? Have you seen why? Understanding is difficult,
but when you understand it, something opens in your heart,
in your mind and then something
called: Consciousness begins to arrive.
It's fashionable! Everyone talks about it,
and no one knows what it is!
Everyone takes courses on "Consciousness,"
courses on I don't know what, and they're... Excuse me, they're still the same!
There is more and more "consciousness," and the world, I don't see it changing!
And there is more and more "awareness"!
—With all the "mindfulness" there is, right? ...
—Yes, yes...Therapists, retreats... People with a diploma
who already have "a conscience."
—In other words, "a diploma certifies your conscience." -But? "You are now a shaman."
—Paying. -Yes of course!
It's okay to investigate, it's okay to search,
but that's where Impeccability comes in: you have to make it authentic.
You have to make it true.
Otherwise, it doesn't work! It is nothing more than a fashion,
it is nothing more than a practice that, due to the euphoria of the moment...
And then, it is forgotten!
Because to walk within those paths, a certain discipline is also required.
No? A certain grit, a certain effort... In all aspects.
—I met a grandfather in Colombia who told me:
"You have no choice but to be what you walk."
—And it sounds easy, right? —Ugh, it's very difficult!
—But point number one: You have to admit it.
—At least, see it. —That which you are that you walk...
Or at least, that which you think you are!
—Which then changes and mutates over time.
—Of course, that's why I'm telling you!
Sometimes we are not even what we thought we were.
So recognition, right? Day to day: You have to live!
And every second counts, you have to live it. We're going away!
You have to leave something, you have to share.
Because what else can we leave? Well, our knowledge, our energy...
Gap, for others who come behind.
Life, as life, contains a principle of reciprocity.
One has to contribute too.
It's a way to honor her. She honors us,
Giving us everything... And what do we give her?
Pure poop!
Every day.
I mean, it sounds stinky and it sounds ugly, and maybe what I say is even grotesque,
but it's the truth!
It's the truth! And anyone who says they don't poop is not human.
—If it were good poop... —Right?
What are we doing? What are we then, then?
A plague?
A bundle of meat and bones?
No, surely not!
It is time to shake off, to dust off certain ideas,
certain schemes that have been imposed for hundreds of years,
that lead us nowhere.
I am not inviting a revolution, or a war...
But, maybe yes, a war. But to an internal war.
To an internal war. TRUE?
Which is the most difficult, the most difficult to get rid of.
That's why here it was called, aptly,
the Florida War: The fight with yourself.
The defeat of your ego, or of your enemy within you.
So that, once you manage to overcome that internal part,
Your heart will flourish; your face becomes true.
You won the Florida War!
And how wonderful it is to understand
that, like a gear in a clock,
an ant, an animal, a plant, a human being
are part of that gear.
Therefore, it has a purpose, it has a function...
Even like the hummingbird, right now, which came to confirm for us, to reaffirm
what we were going to start talking about right now, right?
—What have you learned on the Way of the Warrior?
—To be me, to be me. To be me, as is.
Physically, mentally, spiritually, right? And I accept myself and love myself just the way I am:
short, long hair, dark...
And I like, apart from that, the word "flowery." And I also learned this on the way,
Because the word is sacred.
—This same grandfather I was telling you about before told me:
"Take care of your word, your word will take care of you."
-Well yes. Because if not, that's why I say, you make a mess of yourself.
You make an offense, because another one will come later.
You take care of your word, on the contrary, right?
—And on this path of Impeccability, when we err, what happens there?
—We have to try again because, look:
We have to learn to walk above triumphs and defeats.
One of the premises we have been taught, or schemes,
is that "Everything is a success or everything is a failure."
"Everything is a blessing or everything is a curse."
That's silly!
Because as you walk on the path of life, which is full of networks and holes,
you will surely fall into some.
But greatness is standing up. It is not not falling, but getting up.
So, you have to learn to walk through this world
above triumphs and defeats.
Because everything in life is neither a triumph nor a defeat,
nor is it a curse, nor is it a blessing.
Really, everything is a challenge.
On the same motorcycle that you ride, right?
You skid, you fall... Well, you get up and continue! No?
I don't retreat, I continue. No? Anyway, that's life.
In life there can be no line of happiness.
Because that line of happiness, for me, is even boring.
It's boring! It's everyday.
It's about habits! No, it can not be!
The world is changing, and you have to adapt.
Today you are here; tomorrow you won't be there.
Today you will be happy, today your stew turned out well; not tomorrow.
Projects are like that too, right?
Sometimes you work harder, sometimes you work... There can't be a line.
It would be very boring.
—It seems that there is a certain taboo regarding being sad or feeling bad.
It's like society rewards being good: "It's nice to be good!",
but rather condemns being bad: "Oops! Why would it be bad?"
—But even the one who is apparently happy is not well.
Because it's a mask, because inside they are crying.
Inside they are sad... We are human!
We feel cold, we feel heat, we feel joy, we have longings...
We cannot lie; We can't say no.
For example, they greet me, they say, "How are you?"
"Well happy," Because I try to be happy.
Even though whatever happens.
But I don't like to complain. That's different, isn't it?
"Oh, this happens to me, that happens to me," and I start cursing...
No! Well, it's going to be resolved somehow.
The only thing that cannot be resolved is death; and who knows?
Maybe it's an alternative...
—and the Treasury.
-Ah yeah sure.
—Groucho Marx said it:
"The only thing that has no solution in life is death and the Treasury."
—But, some of us are insurgents and we don't pay the Treasury!
So, you have to live however life comes, right?
Happy, sad... Because, well, there is everything, right?
There is everything, and that's how it is! And that's what makes her rich.
The experience is rich for that reason.
—What does wealth mean to you?
—Well, wealth for me is the accumulation of experiences.
Knowledge, level of understanding.
Truly, if I died and was born again, I would take the same path.
I have loved the path of the Warrior,
the path of Knowledge, the path of my culture.
So, wealth for me is that, right?
The power to understand, the power to understand, the power to know.
Because there are things that material wealth cannot buy,
and one of them is health: mental health, spiritual health.
There are people who are in spiritual holes or in spiritual misery...
Not just economic.
But if you are rich spiritually,
you are going to be rich economically, automatically,
because you are going to have the drive and the drive to do things,
and one way or another, you are going to solve it.
There is a song that says:
"Every day the bird seeks its nest again."
What are you worried about, my brother?
—...Yes, every day the bird has to look for a place to sleep, brother!
When you find your enemy,
which as I understood you, is yourself,
what do you do?
—First you have to know it, you have to identify it.
I'm starting to think, right? And in that thinking,
I see what emotion that thought produces in me,
or what feeling that thought produces in me...
How is my body feeling? How does my heart beat?
Or my liver, right?
And then, there I realize, I begin to realize
the things that affect me or that do not affect me,
or even my own vices:
What do I want more? What do I want less?
What do I long for more? What do I long for less?
In that simplicity, I began to realize
what my strengths were, what my weaknesses were...
But real, real, real, real... And in the simplest way you can.
But you have to be honest.
You have to be very honest! And we are generally not honest.
We deceive ourselves very easily,
or we give reasons for things.
One has to undress completely to see oneself.
So literally, like naked in a mirror
to see what you are like, what you have... What you are.
I say, there is no one method for everyone. It's personal!
It's very personal!
Like spiritual discoveries, they are very personal.
The calls are very personal.
So the method? Well I say, Invent it yourself!
You are the only one who knows how you are.
Not even the best therapist is going to give you the solution.
Maybe He will give you a path, but you walk the path.
And so, you realize that maybe, suddenly you have a possibility,
a talent...
Or even a virtue!
But then comes the other part, which is part of the fight:
Now, exercise it!
Now exercise it! Do not hesitate!
We are full of doubts; We are full of fears.
Because since we were children, we acquired them.
We are surely born free, without fear and without doubts.
But the education of everything around you shapes you.
And when you least see, you are already the same as everyone:
You suffer from everything, you want what everyone does,
you think what everyone does, you wear what everyone does, and you eat what everyone does.
Well I say, That's called colonization!
—In force today, eh? —In force today.
You have to break those things because, what is at stake?
Well, our own lives are at stake!
And it really is difficult to understand.
It is understood, perhaps, mentally:
"Ah, you're just going to be here temporarily",
"Oh no, I mean... we're all going to die",
"Ah, it's true: We're going to die". everyone"
But did you already understand it? Do you really understand it already?
So, get to it now! Because tomorrow may not come.
—But, understanding that...
—That's why I tell you: Understanding, isn't it difficult?
It is not so simple?
You have to move inner keyboards,
certain fibers inside us, for something to move...
And then you say, "Yes, you're right."
—It is difficult to understand something and remain impassive.
-It can't be done.
That's why I tell you: That brings you awareness, to understanding.
And if consciousness comes into your life, I am certain
that it changes from one day to the next.
You can't stay static: You already realized it,
and then you say: "Time does count!
Time has to do with it! No, hurry up, we have little left!"
Because eternal, like this, in this way,
We are not going to be.
We're going to have to go.
Sooner or later, we're going to have to go.
So... There's no need to waste time anymore.
—Are you afraid of having to leave?
-No.
No, it doesn't scare me. I'm not afraid.
I could be uncertain... A little bit, nothing more,
about what could be on the other side, or what's next...
But not afraid.
No fear. What's more, we in Mexico have a saying that goes like this:
"If I have to die tomorrow, let me die once and for all."
Preparing to live is preparing to die.
It seems paradoxical, right?
But it is.
It is! It's something that goes hand in hand.
—Is everything dual?
-Mostly, yes.
But that duality also has a unity.
Ourselves: you have two hands,
two feet, two hemispheres, two eyes...
two nostrils,
two ears... But you are one.
Duality, I think, contains a complexity.
And that complexity, well, it is also a duality.
And it's a plurality, right?
Nothing but everything is taught to us strictly, bluntly,
without stickers, without media: "Either it's white, or it's black."
But between white and black, there is a variety of colors,
of intensities, right? That is what has not been understood.
And it is also what they have misunderstood about Mexican culture,
because Mexican culture talks a lot about duality.
We have no problem understanding the plurality of things,
because the Spirit itself is a diversity of things.
It is an incredible plurality.
And thanks to that plurality, the world exists with all its diversities.
Not only of geographies, but of human beings.
The worldview of Mexico speaks of all that,
of a principle, yes, an abstract principle,
an invisible principle, an impalpable principle, a spark of light.
In Mexico it is called Moyocoyani
and means "He who invents himself and transforms himself."
And that impersonal force, by its own virtue or its own power, unfolded.
And he became an androgynous being, and Ometeotl was born.
And the androgynous is divided in two,
and the man and the woman are born: The dual.
And then the dual creates four children, right? And those four children create four more.
And so it begins, from a unity, to be a duality and then a plurality...
But in the totality of space.
In such a way that the creation of life, from the Mexican angle,
is not created through one element,
but is created through many conjugates...
And then, all those elements can be mixed with each other,
and create something new. And many essences...
But they all come from a beginning.
That is why it is said that everything is sacred and everything is divine,
because that plural divine principle was unfolded in all things.
And one, as an individual, one has to return a little bit
of that honor and that energy, that essence,
because it is so divided that it could die.
Because the plural divine essence is present in all things.
Everything is divine: the wood, the river, the lake, you, your dog, the bird,
the hummingbird, the cloud, the star...
Because everything is captured there. We are all brothers.
As human beings, I say, we are all equal, right?
We have the right to life, the right to eat,
the right to breathe, to think, to live, to have a home... Whatever you want, right?
But the difference is what we keep in our hearts.
So there, we are already different.
Because some keep beautiful things, and some keep very ugly things.
There is a story that says
that before, human beings were telepathic. I didn't even need the Internet.
But as he kept things in his mind and in his heart,
his heart began to close and so did his mind,
and he began to stalk, to long for what was not his.
So it was closing, it was saving, hiding...
Because you could see the other's mind, the other's heart.
As we closed it, the mind closed and the heart closed...
Because we keep things.
So, there's the difference. We are no longer equal.
That is why it is so important to give a true face.
Always a face. The same!
It is very difficult. It's not that easy.
—It is accepting yourself in everything.
—And accept things as they are, too. Because above all, we give a mask:
If you are upset, if you don't like something, if you don't like someone...
You give a mask; You don't show yourself as you are.
By protocols, right? Or by customs, right?
—Social uses.
—Exactly, for social uses.
But for that reason, the person who is sincere, sometimes falls very well, or sometimes falls very badly.
I prefer to be honest.
Even if I fall badly, I don't care. I am not guided by conventions.
I am as I am, and it's over... Period!
Because it is a way, also, to express yourself, what you think, right?
With that, I don't mean that I'm in a position to bother or attack someone.
No, I only say what I think. Nothing else.
—Yes, without your opinion being modulated by possible reactions.
—Of course, yes, yes, yes!
And also, if anyone is interested in my opinion, then let them take it.
If not, then throw it away... I don't care either.
Because I live and think based on a life; to a way of life
and to some convictions... And I'm going on them.
And if I don't live like that, then what am I?
—A puppet. -TRUE?
Well, I prefer to guide my life:
Be the guide of my life.
You could even say that the guide of my destiny.
—Which native civilization here have you learned the most from? From the Toltec?
—From the Toltec and the Nahuatl.
In some way, it begins to open my eyes and I begin to turn to Mexico,
but I begin to see it with the eyes of the inside, that is, with the eyes of Mexico.
Not seeing Mexico with foreign eyes,
but with insider eyes.
How all people have to see themselves:
With their own eyes. And so I began to discover,
to find...
And it was such a beautiful arrangement, that to this day I am in love.
I am in love with Mexican culture... And in fact, with all the cultures of this continent
and with everything that is authentic in the world, right?
In the end I think we are looking for the same thing.
We want the same; We long for the same.
The same thing, in a thousand different ways.
Life is a very beautiful experience.
... Son! Anyone who can't understand it or understand it a little bit...
will even be a hunchback. But, Son, how nice it is to be here! Seriously, how beautiful!
Eat, share, understand, breathe, get on the motorcycle...
See a beautiful sunrise, a good party; then you retreat to your fast to go to the mystical...
How beautiful!
I see that the human being is one of the few beings on planet Earth
that has that capacity for projection.
From projecting inward and projecting outward...
How wonderful!
—What a shame to pass by and not realize it, right?
—There are people who say: "No, this one passed by like a little animal."
No, no, no... worse than an animal!
Because the animal fulfills its function.
They are not speculating what they are going to do, or what they are not going to do.
They fulfill their function.
They behave like what they are... And us?
In our intellect, in our wisdom, in our superiority...
We are further away from ourselves than animals.
What a shame, right? What a pity!
Sometimes, the world hurts me...
The Earth hurts me.
Because you realize things.
Sometimes you want to shout at them, or open them... Kick them up!
To the kicks in the head or in the skin, so that they give...
But, no! They are called personal.
That's why I said: War is personal; Death is personal.
Awakening is personal...
Whoever wants it, well, there it is! Who doesn't...can't be forced either!
But it should be an obligation...
National or spiritual, or global or universal.
Because the more we do it, I believe, we take weight off the world.
It has too much weight already.
Not just with the environmental and physical destruction, right?
With the destruction of thought:
So much that we carry in our heads, in our hearts, in our feelings...
How much weight!
Full of sentimentality, full of tragedies, full of suffering...
Oh, and full of noise! The world is full of external and internal noise.
There are no more pauses, there are no more silences.
There is no longer a retreat from getting a little bit away from that noise, right?
From the noise!
To stay a little to see the mountain from afar,
to see the people from afar... to love them even more!
Because being there, one sometimes fails to see
the greatness of people, things, people... of the world itself.
When you move away a little bit, you see it from a distance. You say: "No, it's worth it. I'm coming back.
I wanted a meteor to fall on the world... But, better not!"
—Yes, it is difficult to deal with the sensations derived from seeing what is happening,
what the path to the solution could be,
and seeing ourselves so far from it, right? As a collective.
—Yes, yes...
Life
has its own evolutionary process.
And with or without me, life will continue to move forward.
What's more, I'm going to die and the sun is going to continue rising;
The birds are going to continue singing...
But I know that things, due to the evolutionary process of life,
sooner or later, are going to fall into place...
Or have to change. Sooner or later!
They are processes.
Our life, as a personal life, or even as a society,
Or as humanity...
If one were to compare it in the process of evolution of life and time...
It is nothing...
It is nothing! A thousand years, two thousand, three thousand years...
In life, they are nothing!
So, what am I in life? Nothing!
Something tiny!
But also, as a certainty,
that from one's perspective, one has to do something for life.
Contribute with a grain of sand.
It doesn't matter if they know it, if they don't know it,
if they understand it or if they don't understand it.
One understands it, one knows it; and you know why he does it.
And if we all thought like that, many cells would come together.
And maybe a process would be faster.
So what's left? Live according to your convictions.
The world is going to continue moving forward.
We will no longer be here, but you lived according to your convictions
for the time you had to live.
And for me, that is the most complete satisfaction
because I know that from the trenches that I am in, with a little or a lot,
I am contributing. Maybe I helped someone,
woke someone up, we shared something, he understood.
Well, what else can you do?
We are not in a position of power to move
the levers of the world and change things.
We are not! We are ordinary men.
But within our ordinariness,
we can change our ordinariness, personally.
And if you change personally and live like that, in that strong way,
you will surely move someone.
He's going to see you! And even if he doesn't tell you, you are going to be his example.
You are going to be their reference.
And it is a way to transcend too.
You have to live according to your convictions,
because that will give you the certainty of being you... Even if others don't understand it and don't know it!
Well, what about that? You know it, don't you?
[On the outskirts of Malinalco, there is a person
who has been carving and sculpting the mountain for almost 30 years,
making the rock his home, his work and his legacy...]
—It is sculpted in the living rock. Here you can see the chisels, look:
Everything I have here is a whole project,
in cultural, spiritual, and environmental preservation.
My project is called Olkeme, because that is the name of this mountain.
And Olkeme means, "He who dresses in movement."
To give something more, be inside the heart of the mountain,
in direct contact with the essence of the Earth.
[He is known as Martin the Builder, guardian of the culture of his ancestors
and an artist driven by a mission:
That whoever visits the place may drink from the knowledge of vision.]
—"The one who dresses in movement"?
—How curious, right?
"Olín" is movement and "kemil" is dress...
"Olkeme".
But, well, it talks about an internal movement, right?
From a movement of the heart: from that which makes you do things, right?
In dynamism, then!
And this has turned out very nice.
It will be useful to future generations, because they are cultural and spiritual references
and we are all in that search, right? ...to be able to understand, to be well...
To reconcile ourselves with the world, or with life or with ourselves.
And why do I do that? Because like many,
I firmly believe that culture is the transversal axis
of the development of human beings.
Now it is seen as folklore, but culture is something very important.
Because as someone said: "It makes
the deepest springs spring from your being."
That's why ethics was born. That's why aesthetics,
poetry, art, science, architecture, medicine, agriculture were born...
For culture!
And now there are people who are university students or professionals,
but they are uneducated. They are ignorant, then!
They know what their career is, their academy; but from there on out, they don't know anything else!
Abysmal ignorance!
In every sense, where they are only looking,
like a mule: "towards the money, towards the money, towards the money..."
And look at the panorama, the beauty, the clouds, the vegetation, the flowers...
The life that embraces us!
You have to fill yourself with life. You have to get infected, you have to become intoxicated with life!
To preserve ancestral memory: Look...
I'm not saying that money is not good or bad...
It is only a means, an instrument
to do certain things, but it is not the goal! That's it: just a means.
Because it comes and goes, it comes back, it goes away, it disappears, it comes back again...
and it's even virtual, if that's how you want to understand it.
An illusion!
But people are wrapped up in that, because they have been told that that is life:
"That is success. That is what gives you value and worth."
Could it be? Will it be true? I do not think so!
Valía will have a person who has human quality.
That one is worth more than a millionaire, who doesn't have that quality,
who maybe with a hug,
makes you feel so good that you say, "Charros, what a joy!"
Or he can even heal you because his embrace is true.
His word is sincere. It's medicine.
How many fucking millionaires,
who don't even know what the money was made for!
Only treasured...
That is why it is so important that the heart flourishes,
that the spirit flourishes... It is very important!
Because later, you disengage from those things and then you share.
—You know it's normal to be called crazy, right?
-Oh yeah. But going crazy has its grip; not everyone arrives.
There are many madmen and many idiots...
But crazy, few.
—The madman is freer than any other; dares to do.
—If that's being crazy, then I am.
So, part of my project is that:
That the people who come here see the archetypes carved in the mountain...
And by going to the heart of the Earth, the idea is that something moves inside you.
If possible, awaken your memory or remember...
Because also, there is a song that says,
"And how can I not sing, If I have everything to be happy?
I have the moon and I have the sun. I have energy and I am warm,
And to the mountain to share Your person, who is here."
-What do you dream?
—What I live. I have learned to be the dream and the dreamer,
And I live this: Life.
That's why I like poetry, because poetry has to be lived.
You live and you dream.
And keep quiet what I say, and dream what I forget.
And it is a saying that is a doing...
And as soon as you say: "It's real," it dissipates.
But here we are, living it.
For moments, for moments, for moments...
Beauty!
Beauty embodied in all things.
In ourself.
Long live life, and long live you!